have you ever heard about the war
between Canada and Denmark this conflict
is better known as the whiskey war or
the liquor War however it cannot be
called a war in the traditional
sense let's find out what happened and
why it has such a strange name the
reason for this conflict was this tiny
piece of land called Hans Island it's 12
90 M long and 1199 M wide this
uninhabited Island looks more like a
but it created a whole history of the
world famous conflict between Canada and
Denmark that lasted almost 50
years the first question that might come
up is what do these two countries about
4,000 km apart have in common with this
island first let's have a look at
Greenland Greenland is the largest
island in the world mostly covered by
glaciers with the extreme Arctic climate
in 19 1953 Greenland was redefined as a
district of the Kingdom of Denmark which
resulted in the creation of a common
border with Canada and as it turned out
the Border passed in the middle of Hans
Island the island is exactly 18 km away
from both Canada and Denmark allowing
both countries to claim the land under
international
law 1973 is considered to be the year of
the beginning of the whiskey War Canada
and Denmark signed a treaty to demarcate
the maritime border between elisir
Island and Greenland the treaty
deliberately left the border at hans's
Island undefined as both States claimed
Hans Island as part of their
territory in 1984 something interesting
happened the Danish Minister for
Greenland Tom hoyam arrived on the
island planted the national flag and
left a bottle of schnaps along with a
message something similar to Welcome to
the Danish
Island how do you think Canada re
reacted declared war and sent troops
well Canadian soldiers visited the
island removed the Denmark flag planted
a Canadian flag and left a bottle of
Canadian whiskey along with a note
welcome to
Canada this practice of leaving bottles
of liquor next to the flags continued
for several decades with both countries
periodically exchanging the bottles and
flags as part of a light-hearted
tradition Canadian whiskey or Danish
schnaps became the symbol of a whiskey
War over the
island in 2005 the foreign Ministers of
Canada and Denmark met in New York and
announced willingness to resolve the
conflict stating that a war of flags was
unacceptable in the modern world and
only in 2022 the turning point was
Russia's invasion of Ukraine thus
unleashing the largest war in Europe
since World War II Canada and Denmark
signed an agreement to end the conflict
setting an example for other countries
on how to resolve territorial disputes
it sends a message to the world and also
including President Putin what happened
with the Russia's invasion of Ukraine
and so it's symbolic because it at the
time where it's happening as we're
seeing that there's an illegal and
unjustifiable Invasion under the terms
of the peace agreement the island was
divided along a north south Clift in its
Center 60% of the island went to Denmark
and the remaining 40% to Canada
and traditionally the parties exchanged
bottles of
alcohol I am confident this is the way
Wars should be fought in the modern
world